Finding Aid for Pearl L. Kendrick Papers 1888-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Pearl L. Kendrick Papers
1888-1979
1930-1970
Kendrick, Pearl L., 1890-1980.
Bacteriologist with the laboratories of the Michigan Department of Health, 1920-1951, and resident lecturer in epidemiology at the School of Public Health of the University of Michigan. Files relate to her discovery and testing of a vaccine for whooping-cough; files concerning activities with the American Public Health Association and the Michigan Public Health Association; consultant's files relating to her work with vaccination programs in foreign countries under the auspices of the World Health Organization; correspondence, course and research materials; and photographs related to her career; also papers of her father, Milton Kendrick, a Free Methodist clergyman.
85242 Aa 2
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection (Donor no. 5681 ) was donated by Pearl Kendrick in 1979. A smaller accession was received from the estate of Dr. Grace Eldering in 1988.
The collection is open for research.
Pearl Luella Kendrick (1890-1980) was born August 24, 1890 in Wheaton, Illinois. She was the daughter of Ella (Shaver) Kendrick and Milton H. Kendrick, a Free Methodist (Holiness) preacher in New York state. Pearl Kendrick attended high school in Sherburne, New York, graduating in 1908. She enrolled in Greenville College, Greenville, Illinois, in 1910 but after her first year transferred to Syracuse University, from which she received a B.S. in 1914. Kendrick taught in rural schools after her graduation from high school and for five years after graduating from college she taught science and served as a principal in New York high schools. In 1919 and 1920 she worked as a laboratory assistant in the division of laboratories and research of the New York State Department of Health.
Kendrick moved to Lansing, Michigan, in 1920 to work as a bacteriologist in the Michigan Department of Health laboratory. In 1926 she was appointed Associate Director of Laboratories and Chief of the Western Michigan Branch Laboratory of the Michigan Department of Health in Grand Rapids. She pursued a graduate degree during leaves of absence and earned an Sc.D. from the Johns Hopkins University School of Hygiene and Public Health in 1932.
Kendrick's most important work was done at the Michigan Department of Health, where she carried out extensive studies on the diagnosis and prevention of whooping cough. Whooping cough was one of the most serious diseases of young children in the early 1930s, claiming approximately 6000 lives annually in the United States. Kendrick and her colleagues undertook an investigation of the pertussis bacillus, the etiologic agent of whooping cough, and in 1934 began a series of field trials to test the pertussis vaccine. Forty years later Grace Eldering, Kendrick's colleague, longtime companion, and successor as Chief of the Western Michigan Branch Laboratory of the Michigan Department of Health, recalled tramping the streets of Grand Rapids to gather specimens for the study:
As soon as the laboratory closed in the afternoon, we set out to find new patients. The early 1930s were years of the great depression, and we learned about the disease and the depression at the same time. Many of the families we visited were very poor and their living conditions pitiful. Our watchword became 'Round to the back and up the stairs.' We listened to sad stories told by desperate fathers who could find no work. We collected specimens by the light of kerosene lamps, from whooping, vomiting, strangling children. We saw what the disease could do.
Although a pertussis vaccine had been prepared in the first decade of the twentieth century, confidence in its efficacy had declined because of the lack of adequate testing. Kendrick's field study demonstrated the effectiveness of pertussis vaccine and also helped establish the field trial as an important method for measuring immunization. In 1940 the Michigan Department of Health started general distribution of the vaccine.
Because of her success with the pertussis vaccine, Kendrick was asked to act as a consultant on immunization projects and pertussis studies in a number of foreign countries. In 1940 and 1942 Kendrick assisted with whooping cough studies being carried out by the Ministry of Health of Mexico. Between 1949 and 1965 Kendrick served periodically as a World Health Organization consultant to various countries--most often in Latin America--setting up immunization programs. Kendrick was also a member of the Immunology Delegation that visited laboratories in the Soviet Union in 1962 as part of a United States-Union of Soviet Socialist Republics exchange program.
From 1951 until her retirement in 1960 Kendrick was a lecturer in the Department of Epidemiology in the School of Public Health at the University of Michigan. She continued her study of the pertussis vaccine at the University, and also worked to develop multi-purpose vaccines. Kendrick was active in professional associations throughout her career, serving as chairman of several committees of the American Public Health Association. She died in 1980.
The Pearl L. Kendrick papers date from 1888 to 1979 and measure seven linear feet. The papers are arranged in nine series: Personal, Correspondence, Correspondence--Foreign, Michigan Department of Health, University of Michigan, Consultant Files, Professional Associations, Speeches and Articles, and Visual Materials. The collection is strongest in its documentation of the national and international network of public health practitioners, physicians, and scientists who corresponded with each other about their studies of various diseases and their prevention, in particular whooping cough. This voluminous correspondence reflects Kendrick's reputation as one of the world's foremost experts on pertussis. The collection is relatively weak in its documentation of Kendrick's work as an instructor at the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
American Public Health Association.; Bacteriologists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Clergy--Michigan.; Epidemiology.; Kendrick, Pearl L., 1890-1980.; Michigan. Dept. of Health.; Michigan Public Health Association.; Public health--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; Whooping-cough.; Women bacteriologists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World Health Organization.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Laboratories.; Soviet Union.; Women.
Contributors:
Atwater, Reginald Myers, 1892-1957.; Bayne-Jones, Stanhope, 1888-1970; Cockburn, Charles.; Cohen, Barnett, 1891-1952.; Cummings, George Donald, 1904-1967.; Doull, James Angus, 1889-1963.; Eldering, Grace, 1900-; Evans, David G.; Frost, Wade Hampton, 1880-1938.; Kendrick, Milton.; Lacey, Brian.; Pillemer, Louis, 1908-1957.; Pittman, Margaret, 1901-; Verwey, Willard Foster, 1913-1979.; Williams, R. E. O. (Robert Evan Owen); Young, Clifford Caudy, 1885-1944.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Personal, 1888-1979
  The first series, Personal (1888-1979), includes biographical information, vitae, material relating to Kendrick's employment, correspondence with family and friends, and diaries of a personal nature. Also in this series are journals, reminiscences, accounts, and sermons of Kendrick's father, Milton Kendrick, a Free Methodist (Holiness) preacher.
  - Biographical and Genealogical Information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1942-1966; undated (Box 1)
    - Family, 1922-1979; undated (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    - 1920s-1960s, undated [fragments] (Box 1)
    - [trip to London], 1936 (Box 1)
    - [fragment], 1940s (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 1)
    - [trip to Europe], 1958 (Box 1)
    - [trip to Europe], 1959 (Box 1)
  - Education
    - University of Michigan, 1924; 1930 (Box 1)
  - Employment
    - Letters of Recommendation, 1914-1919 (Box 1)
    - Teaching Positions, 1914-1919 (Box 1)
    - New York State Department of Health, 1920; 1923 (Box 1)
  - Honors and Awards, 1958-1978 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Kendrick, Milton
    - Journal, 1888-1901 (Box 1)
    - Journals and Accounts, 2 volumes in 1 folder (Box 1)
    - Sermons and Miscellaneous Notes (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: Excerpts from Major Tripp's Letters to Mrs. Tripp, 1944 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1950-1969
  Correspondence dates primarily from the 1950s and 1960s and consists of correspondence, both incoming and outgoing, with academic and commercial laboratory scientists and public health practitioners. This correspondence relates largely to Kendrick's research and teaching at the University of Michigan and includes requests for cultures and sera, discussion of laboratory techniques and biologic products, and, more generally, certain diseases and their prevention. The series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - A-Bl, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Blodgett Memorial Hospital, 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - Bo-C, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Communicable Disease Center, 1951-1970; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - D (Box 1)
  - Difco Laboratories, Detroit, 1952-1957 (Box 1)
  - E (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica (Box 1)
  - Eveland, W.C., 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - F (Box 1)
  - Francis, Thomas, 1957-1963 (Box 1)
  - G-H, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hospital Infections Committee (Box 2)
  - I-L, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Lilly Research Laboratories, 1951-1962 (Box 2)
  - M (Box 2)
  - Merck Sharp and Dohme Research Laboratories, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Department of Health
    - General, 1951-1970 (Box 2)
    - Anderson, H.D., 1951-1963 (Box 2)
    - Cummings, G.D., 1951-1965 (Box 2)
    - Eldering, Grace, 1952-1966 (Box 2)
    - Ferguson, William, 1951-1958 (Box 2)
  - N (Box 2)
  - National Institutes of Health
    - General, 1951-1968 (Box 2)
    - Pertussis Symposium, 1963 (Box 2)
      (see also: Pittman, Margaret)
  - New York State Department of Health, 1952-1961 (Box 2)
  - O-P, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Parke, Davis and Company, 1953-1966 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Pfizer (Chas) and Company, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Pillemer, Louis, 1952-1957 (Box 2)
  - Pittman, Margaret, 1951-1979; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - R-S, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Siebold, H.R., 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - T-V, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - UNICEF, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Venereal Disease Research Laboratory, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Volk, V.K., 1952-1970 (Box 2)
  - W (Box 2)
  - Wilson, Robert J., 1959-1968 (Box 2)
  - X-Z (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Foreign, 1939-1970
  Correspondence--Foreign (1939-1970) is comprised of correspondence with doctors and scientists in foreign countries, mostly on the subject of pertussis vaccine. Most countries, with the exception of England, are represented by only a few items; the British subseries includes substantive correspondence with several eminent scientists and physicians over a span of years. The series is arranged alphabetically by country.
  - Argentina, 1954-1955; 1963 (Box 2)
  - Brazil, 1955-1970 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Canada, 1952-1968 (Box 2)
  - Costa Rica, 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Denmark, 1953-1963 (Box 2)
  - England
    - General, 1939-1966 (scattered); 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Cockburn, Charles, 1952-1958 (Box 2)
    - Evans, David G., 1951-1959 (Box 3)
    - Lacey, Brian, 1953-1959 (Box 3)
    - Whooping Cough Committee, 1943-1952; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Williams, R.E.O., 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - France, 1952-1966 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Germany, 1952-1969 (Box 3)
  - Hungary, 1954-1961 (Box 3)
  - India, 1954-1966 (Box 3)
  - Iran, 1953; 1967 (Box 3)
  - Israel, 1952-1955 (Box 3)
  - Italy, 1954-1961 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Japan, 1951-1970 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Mexico, 1952-1970 (Box 3)
  - The Netherlands, 1952-1968 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - El Salvador, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Scot, 1952; 1958-1965 (Box 3)
  - South Africa, 1949-1952 (Box 3)
  - Spain, 1952-1955 (Box 3)
  - Switzer, 1953-1959 (Box 3)
  - Taiwan, 1952-1966 (Box 3)
  - Turkey, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Venezuela, 1966; 1970 (Box 3)
  - Yugoslavia, 1953-1965 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Countries (Box 3)
- Michigan Department of Health, 1920-1953
  Michigan Department of Health (1920-1953) consists for the most part of correspondence, together with some research notebooks, relating to the pertussis field studies in Grand Rapids and the work of other scientists on pertussis.
  - General (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1934-1946 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Breed, Robert S., 1945-1946 (Box 3)
    - Young, C.C., 1926-1944; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Employment, 1920-1951 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - History (Box 3)
  - Pertussis Studies
    - Code Manual, 1939 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1934-1948 (scattered) (Box 3)
      - Alexander, Hattie E., 1937; 1945-1952 (Box 3)
      - Bayne-Jones, Stanhope, 1932-1933 (Box 3)
      - Bunney, W.E., 1939-1953 (Box 3)
      - Cohen, Barnett, 1940-1950 (scattered) (Box 3)
      - Densen, Paul M., 1950 (Box 3)
      - Doull, James A., 1936-1945 (Box 3)
      - Evans, David G., 1946 (Box 3)
      - Fraser, Donald T., 1937-1952 (Box 3)
      - Frost, W.H., 1936-1938 (Box 3)
      - Lawson, George M., 1933-1948; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Miller, John J., 1934-1952 (scattered) (Box 3)
      - National Institutes of Health, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
      - National Research Council, 1934-1938 (Box 3)
      - Perkins, James E., 1940-1942; 1950 (Box 3)
      - Pittman, Margaret, 1945-1950 (Box 3)
      - Ramsey, George H., 1935-1938 (Box 3)
      - Toomey, John A., 1946-1948 (Box 3)
      - Vaughan, Henry, 1938 (Box 3)
      - Verwey, W.F., 1942-1946; 1951-1953 (Box 3)
      - Weiss, Edward S., 1941-1942 (Box 3)
      - Zozaya, Jose, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Density Comparisons, 1943 (Box 4)
    - Funding, 1942-1951; 1972 (Box 4)
    - History, 1936; 1971 (Box 4)
    - Mouse Protection Test, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
    - Outline of Work, 1946-1951 (Box 4)
    - Pertussis Committee, 1951-1953 (Box 4)
    - Pertussis Medium, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Plans I--Review by Dr. W.H. Frost, 1936-1937 (Box 4)
    - Plans II, 1934-1938 (Box 4)
    - Research Notebook, 1940 (Box 4)
    - Salaries, 1937 (Box 4)
    - "Whooping Cough Prevention: A Review,", 1938 (Box 4)
    - Works Progress Administration, 1936 (Box 4)
- University of Michigan, 1952-1975
  University of Michigan (1952-1975) consists of material relating to Kendrick's teaching and research at the University of Michigan in the Department of Epidemiology. Only a few of her lectures are included.
  - General
    - Annuitants' Society, 1962-1972 (Box 4)
    - Women's Research Club, 1953; 1967 (Box 4)
  - Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health
    - Annual Report to the Dean, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1970 (Box 4)
    - Delta Omega
      - General, 1968 (Box 4)
      - Delta Omega Lecture
        - Marston Bates: "The Population Explosion", 1960 (Box 4)
        - James Dixon: "Public Health: The Art of the Possible", 1963 (Box 4)
    - Employment Information (Box 4)
    - Epidemiology Lectures and Syllabi (Box 4)
    - Gudakunst Lecture, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Memoranda and Reports, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
    - Research
      - Experiments
        - 1956-1961 (Box 4)
        - Pertussis, 1963-1964; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Saginaw Study of DPT-Polio, 1963 (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Procedures
        - Fluorescent Antibody Procedures, 1959; 1961 (Box 4)
        - Gel Diffusion and Immuno-Electrophoresis, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Consultant files, 1940-1970
  Consultant Files (1940-1970) includes correspondence, diaries, and reports of Kendrick's work for the World Health Organization and as an independent consultant on pertussis. The series is arranged chronologically by assignment.
  - General
    - Mexico Department of Health, 1942
      - Correspondence, 1940-1946 (Box 4)
      - Reports, 1942 (Box 4)
    - United States-Union of Soviet Socialist Republics Exchange, 1962
      - Health Services Delegation: Report by David Sencer (Box 4)
      - Immunology Delegation
        - Correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 4)
        - Diary (Box 4)
        - Report, 1962; 1 volumes (Box 4)
        - Report, 1962 (Box 4)
  - World Health Organization
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1949-1970 (Box 5)
      - Pan American Sanitary Bureau, 1950-1956; 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - Statistics, 1930-1950 (Box 5)
    - England and South America Trip, 1949-1950
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1949-1954 (Box 5)
        - Brazil, 1950-1956 (Box 5)
        - Chile, 1950-1956; 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Colombia, 1950-1954; 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Eldering, Grace (Box 5)
        - Eng, 1950 (Box 5)
        - Peru, 1953-1954 (Box 5)
      - Diaries
        - Eng, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
        - South America, 1950; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Dubrovnik Conference on Diphtheria and Pertussis Vaccines, October 1952
      - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 5)
      - Diary (Box 5)
      - Draft Report (Box 5)
      - Kendrick Talk, May 1953 (Box 5)
      - Notes (Box 5)
      - Working Papers (Box 5)
    - Mexico Trip, 1961
      - Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 5)
      - Report to World Health Organization, 1961 (Box 5)
      - Schedule and Minutes--Working Group on Whooping Cough, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Working Group on the Latin American Common Market for Biological Products Meeting, August 1964
      - Reports (Box 5)
    - South America Trip, 1964-1965
      - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 5)
      - Countries Visited
        - Brazil (Box 5)
        - Chile (Box 5)
        - Guatemala (Box 5)
        - Panama (Box 5)
        - Uruguay (Box 5)
        - Venezuela (Box 5)
      - Diaries (Box 6)
      - Report to Pan American Health Organization (PAHO), 1965 (Box 6)
      - Staff Meeting in Ann Arbor, March 24, 1965 (Box 6)
- Professional Associations, 1936-1972
  Correspondence, minutes, reports, and related material make up the Professional Associations series (1936-1972), documenting Kendrick's membership in various professional associations. The bulk of this series relates to her work with the American Public Health Association, particularly its Multiple Antigen Committee and other committees.
  - American Academy of Microbiology, 1957-1969 (Box 6)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1969 (Box 6)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences, 1962-1964 (Box 6)
  - American Public Health Association
    - General (Box 6)
    - Committees and Sections
      - Antigen Committees (Box 6)
      - Committee on Administrative Practice, 1936-1938; 1948 (Box 6)
      - Committee on Research and Standards, 1951-1956
        - Correspondence, 1947; 1951-1956 (Box 6)
        - Minutes, 1951-1956 (Box 6)
      - Committee on Whooping Cough, 1936 (Box 6)
      - Coordinating Committee on Laboratory Methods
        - General, 1951-1956 (Box 6)
        - Correspondence, 1950-1958 (Box 6)
        - Meeting Notes, March 1948 (Box 6)
        - Nominating Committee, 1955-1957 (Box 6)
      - Epidemiology Section: Technical Committee on Immunization
        - Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 6)
        - Minutes, 1961-1966 (Box 6)
      - Historical Sketch of Immunization and Multiple Antigen Committees (Box 6)
      - Laboratory Section
        - Correspondence, 1951-1970 (scattered) (Box 6)
        - Public Health Laboratory Directors--Conference, 1968 (Box 6)
      - Multiple Antigen Committee
        - Correspondence, 1951-1961; 4 folders (Box 6)
        - Meetings, 1954-1964; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Reports, 1956-1961 (Box 6)
      - Subcommittee on Diagnostic Procedures and Reagents
        - Correspondence
          - 1953-1955 (Box 6)
          - 1959-1962 (Box 6)
        - Memoranda, 1953-1954 (Box 6)
      - Subcommittee on Enteric Phage Typing, 1948-1954 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1954-1958 (Box 7)
      - Atwater, Reginald, 1951-1957 (Box 7)
      - Elder, Francis, 1951-1958 (Box 7)
    - Executive Board
      - Meeting Notes, February 1947 (Box 7)
      - Special Committee on Future Policies, 1950-1951 (Box 7)
    - Lasker Awards, 1953-1960 (Box 7)
    - Pertussis Study
      - Annual Reports, 1942-1955 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1938-1955; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Early Plans Toward Standardization, 1952-1954 (Box 7)
      - Final Report, 1954 (Box 7)
    - "Why Join the APHA?" by Pearl Kendrick, 1947 (Box 7)
  - American Society for Microbiology
    - General, 1968-1971 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Branch, 1969-1972 (Box 7)
  - Clinical Laboratory Association, Mexico, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Conference of Public Health Laboratory Directors
    - Annual Meetings, 1961; 1965; 1968 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1954 (Box 7)
  - International Congress for Microbiology, 1958; 1970 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, 1955; 1968-1970 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Public Health Association
    - General, 1969 (Box 7)
    - Annual Conference, 1965; 1967 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 7)
    - Laboratory Division, 1969-1971 (Box 7)
    - Newsletters, 1967-1971 (scattered) (Box 7)
    - Resolutions Committee, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Michigan State Medical Society: Child Welfare Committee--Subcommittee on Revision of Immunization Procedures, 1942-1943 (Box 7)
  - New York Academy of Sciences, 1956; 1965 (Box 7)
  - Society for General Microbiology, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Society of American Bacteriologists, 1957-1961 (Box 7)
- Speeches and Articles
  Reprints of articles by Kendrick and Grace Eldering, along with a few speeches and unpublished articles, comprise the Speeches and Articles series.
  - Reprints
    - Collected Reprints of Pearl L. Kendrick and Grace Eldering, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Reprints (Box 7)
  - Speeches, 1954-1976 (scattered) (Box 7)
- Visual Materials
  The final series Visual Materials includes photographs from her career and travels, and a videotape of a lecture given in 1977 relating to whooping cough and the World Health Organization.
  - Photographs
    - Career (Box 7)
    - Family (Box 7)
    - Portraits (Box 7)
    - Travels (Box 7)
    - United States--Union of Soviet Socialist Republics Exchange: Immunology Delegation, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Videotapes
    - Videotape of lecture by Pearl Kendrick and Grace Eldering relating to whooping cough and the World Health Organization, U-matic, ca. 60 min. (Box 7)
Related Material
Researchers may also wish to consult the Grace Eldering papers at the State Archives of Michigan in Lansing, as well as numerous collections at the Bentley Historical Library documenting the University of Michigan School of Public Health and its faculty.